Guide to the Walt Whitman papers, 1841-1940, bulk 1841-1891 RL.01378
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Clippings, 1845-1891 and undated, bulk 1845-1855
  - "The French Moralists" (Volume 152)
    Description from Frey: American Whig Review, ii (November, 1845), 497-504. An article on La Bruyere, Montaigne, and Nicole, with a few annotations by Whitman. On page 497 are mounted clippings on French literature and on John Clare and John Dryden, all dated 1857. On page 504 is mounted a clipping consisting of a review of A. de Tocqueville's The Old Regime and the Revolution, translated by John Bonner; endorsed "Oct. '56." Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "Hymn of Callimachus" "Miss Barrett's Poems" (Volume 153)
    Description from Frey: American Whig Review, 1 (January, 1845), 35-48. A translation of a portion of the "Hymn of Callimachus" and a review of E. B. Barrett's A Drama of Exile, and Other Poems; Whitman has written on page 35 the titles of both articles. With two pages from the United States Democratic Review (xvii (December, 1845), 453-454), on the second of which begins a review of Bailey's Festus. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "Hymn of Heavenly Beauty" (Volume 154)
    Description from Frey: Half-Hours with the Best Authors, 1, 207-216. A copy of the poem, with a brief introductory sketch on Spenser; with one annotation by Whitman. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "John Bunyan" (Volume 155)
    Description from Frey: Two clippings on Bunyan, both from Macaulay; the second consists of pages 527-534 from Half-Hours with the Best Authors, 1. With a few annotations by Whitman. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "Literature of the Middle Ages" (Volume 181)
    Description from Frey: Westminster Review, American edition, li (July, 1849), 181-192. A portion of a review of Villemain's Literature of the Middle Ages, with several annotations by Whitman. Two clippings, on Gerard de Nerval and on the difference between American and French journalism, are mounted on page 192. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "Modern Poetry and Poets" (Volume 156)
    Description from Frey: Edinburgh Review, American edition, xc (October, 1849), 203-228. A review of works by Tennyson, Shelley, and Keats, with several annotations by Whitman. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "New English Poets" (Volume 157)
    Description from Frey: Putnam's Monthly, vi (September, 1855), 225-238. Review of volumes of poetry by Owen Meredith and Matthew Arnold, with one annotation by Whitman. At the bottom of the last page is mounted a clipping describing the new lecture room at the Smithsonian Institution, endorsed "Aug. 23d 1856 Eagle." Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "One Thousand Historical Events, with the Dates" (Volume 187)
    Description from Frey: Memoria Technica, pages 17-40, with several annotations by Whitman. Enclosed in a wrapper of four sheets of yellow paper; on the third of these, Whitman mounted two clippings, one headed "Origin and unchangeable nature of Plants and Animals," endorsed "American Institute, Farm ers' Club April 21 '57," the other on the human tendency to exalt the past. On the last sheet of the wrapper he mounted two scraps of manuscript, forty-three lines in pen cil, dealing with Moses, Sesostris, dates in early Greek his tory, and "Attitudes and expressions of fire company return'g [s] lowly home." In a board folder.
  - "Phrenology: A Socratic Dialogue" (Volume 159)
    Description from Frey: American Whig Review, in (January, 1846), 31-46. An article by J. D. Whelpley, with a few annotations by Whitman. With "The Standard Civilized Head" (Life Illustrated, n.s., ii (July 5, 1856), 74), a clipping mounted on miscellaneous printed sheets. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "The Poetry of Sacred and Legendary Art" (Volume 160)
    Description from Frey: Blackwood's Edinburgh Magazine, lxv (February, 1849), 175-190. A review of a book by Mrs. Jameson, slightly annotated by Whitman. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "Political Poets: Waller and Marvell" (Volume 161)
    Description from Frey: American Whig Review, N.s., vii (May, 1851), 411-418. An article, with a few annotations by Whitman. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "Pope" (Volume 162)
    Description from Frey: North British Review, American edition, ix (August, 1848), 163-182. A review of Roscoe's edition of The Works of Alexander Pope, with a few annotations by Whitman. Inserted between pages 168 and 169 is a copy of Pope's "Imitation of Horace" clipped from the anthology Half-Hours with the Best Authors (i, 427-432). Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "The Prelude" (Volume 163)
    Description from Frey: American Whig Review, n.s., vii (May, 1851), 447-448, 455-458. Portions of a review of Wordsworth's Prelude, with a few annotations by Whitman. On page 447 is printed a translation from Uhland, "Crossing the Ferry"; Whitman has written in a variation of the last stanza, which he evidently recalled from another translation, published in the same magazine (iv (December, 1846), 584). On the same page is mounted a clipping on Leigh Hunt's self-criticism, annotated by Whitman. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - Progress: Its Law and Cause "Literature and Society" (Volume 183)
    Description from Frey: Westminster Review, American edition, lxvii (April, 1857), 243-266, 277-288. Two reviews: the first deals with books by Alexander von Humboldt, Sir Charles Lyell, and W. B. Carpenter, the second with Lord John Russell's edition of the Memoirs, Journal and Correspondence of Thomas Moore; with several annotations by Whitman. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "The Prose Writers of America" "New Poetry in New-England" (Volume 164)
    Description from Frey: United States Democratic Review, xx (May, 1847), 383- 398. Reviews of Griswold's The Prose Writers of America and of volumes of poetry by Emerson and others; Whitman has made several annotations on the passage dealing with Emerson. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "Provencal and Scandinavian Poetry" (Volume 165)
    Description from Frey: Edinburgh Review, American edition, lxxxviii (July, 1848), 1-16. A review of works by Fauriel, Dinaux, and others, with several annotations by Whitman. On page 1is mounted a brief clipping on the saga. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "Recollections of Poets Laureate. Wordsworth: Tennyson" (Volume 166)
    Description from Frey: American Whig Review, n.s., ix (June, 1852), 515-524. An article, with several annotations by Whitman. Inserted between pages 516-517 is a clipping on the appearance of Wordsworth. Bound in a royal octavo volume, boards.
  - "R. M. Milnes' Life of Keats" (Volume 167)
    Description from Frey: North British Review, American edition, x (November, 1848), 39-52. A review, with a few annotations by Whitman. Mounted at the top of page 39 is a clipping on the Italian poet, Paolo Giacometti, endorsed "N. Y. Herald Sept. 8 '56." Bound in a royal octavo volume, boards.
  - "The Romantic in Literature and Art" (Volume 184)
    Description from Frey: Sartain's Magazine, v (November, 1849), 297-304. An article by Charles G. Leland, with one annotation by Whitman, as follows: "This essay has many good suggestion—the principal fault is that 'Romantic' is not the right word to use, as used in it—(what should be the word?)." Poe's "The Bells" appears on page 304. In a board folder.
  - "Scottish Poetry Robert Burns" (Volume 168)
    Description from Frey: Two sections clipped from an anthology, pages 399-408; with several annotations by Whitman. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "Shakespeare's Sonnets" (Volume 169)
    Description from Frey: Sartain's Magazine, v (September and October, 1849), 153-158, 217-224. Two parts of an article by John S. Hart, with several passages underlined by Whitman. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "The Standard Civilized Head" (Box 14)
    Description from Frey: Life Illustrated, n.s., ii (July 5, 1856), 74, a clipping mounted on miscellaneous printed sheets. Bound in an octavo volume, boards. With "Phrenology: A Socratic Dialogue."
  - "Taylor's Eve of the Conquest" (Volume 170)
    Description from Frey: Edinburgh Review, American edition, lxxxix (April, 1849), 183-196. A portion of a review, with numerous annotations by Whitman. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "Tennyson's Poems" (Volume 171)
    Description from Frey: Blackwood's Edinburgh Magazine, lxv (April, 1849), 453- 468. A review of Tennyson's Poems and The Princess, with several annotations by Whitman. On page 467 is mounted a clipping, "English Gossip." Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "Tennyson's Poems —The Princess" (Volume 172)
    Description from Frey: North British Review, American edition, ix (May, 1848), 25-40. A portion of a review, slightly annotated by Whitman. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "Thoughts on Reading" (Volume 173)
    Description from Frey: American Whig Review, 1 (May, 1845), 483-496. An article, with several annotations by Whitman. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "Translators of Homer" (Volume 174)
    Description from Frey: American Whig Review, iv (October, 1846), 351-372. An article by C. A. Bristed, with several annotations by Whitman. Inserted between pages 366-367 is a portion of a page clipped from Thoreau's A Week on the Concord and Merrimack Rivers, giving translations of several passages from Pindar. A clipping on translations of the Iliad is mounted at the bottom of page 372. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "The Vanity and the Glory of Literature" (Volume 175)
    Description from Frey: Edinburgh Review, American edition, lxxxix (April, 1849), 149-168. An article on The London Catalogue... 1814 to 1846, with numerous annotations by Whitman. A clip ping on the Muses is mounted at the top of page 149; one on Socratic philosophy, at the bottom of page 168. Bound in an octavo volume, boards.
  - "Voltaire" (Volume 176)
    Description from Frey: Life Illustrated, n.s., ii (May 10, 1856), 9. Whitman's article on Voltaire, mounted on a sheet of yellow paper and annotated by the author. In a board folder.
  - Whitman's Annotations on Magazine Excerpts, Clippings, Etc., undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Transcripts of Whitman's annotations on magazine excerpts, newspaper clippings, etc.
- Material About or Relating to Whitman, 1849-1892 and undated
  Contains the manuscript of Richard Maurice Bucke's biography of Whitman, and some personal manuscript material of Whitman's, including copies of his will drawn up by Bucke.
  - Other Manuscripts About Whitman, 1849-1892 and undated
    Manuscript versions of drafts and notes on Whitman's career. Listed alphabetically by author.
    - Bucke, Richard Maurice
      - "Walt Whitman: Man and Poet" (Volume 146)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript of an essay or lecture, fifteen pages; in a notebook with tan wrappers. Laid in: a chart of Whitman's ancestors, also in Bucke's autograph. In a board folder.
      - Wills of Walt Whitman (Volume 150)
        Description from Frey: Copies of wills made by Whitman in 1872, 1880, and 1882, and of accompanying letters (1872) to his mother and to George Whitman, in the autograph of R. M. Bucke, dated Burlington, N. J., April 1, 1892; seven pages. Bound in a small quarto volume, blue morocco back.
    - Fowler, L. N.
      - "Phrenological Description of W. {Age 29 Occupation Printer} Whitman by L. N. Fowler N. York July 16—1849" (Volume 148)
        Description from Frey: Manuscript of Fowler's description, six pages; with the list and numbers describing Whitman's "bumps," in the autograph of R. M. Bucke, five pages. With a magazine excerpt, "Physiognomy," Quarterly Review, American edition, xc (January, 1852), 33-48; part of an article on Samuel Rogers, American Phrenological Journal, xxiv (August, 1856), 36-38; a prospectus for the American Phrenological Journal; and eleven clippings from newspapers and magazines, on phrenology, longevity, per sonal magnetism, and related subjects; annotated by Whitman. In a quarto volume, half green morocco.
  - Richard Maurice Bucke's Biography of Whitman, circa 1880-1883
    Consists of draft manuscript material by Bucke, William O'Connor, and Whitman that was later revised and used in Bucke's Walt Whitman. Also contains large portions of Bucke's revised manuscript.
    - Draft Manuscripts
      - "The fifteen years from 1840 to 1855 may be considered" (Volume 139)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript by Walt Whitman, written in pencil on one sheet of paper, about 11x8 inches, one side only; twenty lines, extensively revised. Bound in a quarto volume, cloth, green morocco back. An early draft of several sentences appearing, in a much altered form, in Bucke's biography (page 136). With an envelope endorsed by Whitman: "Walt Whitman —the fif teen years from 1840 to 1855."
    - Revised Manuscripts
      - Seven Portions of the Revised Manuscript of Bucke's Walt Whitman (Volume 140)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript by Walt Whitman, written in ink on six sheets of paper, about 9x8 inches (many passages written on scraps of paper of various sizes, mounted on brown sheets or pasted together); about 130 lines, heavily revised, with instructions to the printer inserted in red ink. Bound in a quarto volume, full green morocco, gilt tooled. An outline of Whitman's life, used by Bucke in the introduction to his biography of the poet. Various fragments appear on the verso of the scraps: second page—two fragments of letters, one from D. M. Zimmerman, an official of the Camden and Atlantic Railroad Company, acknowledging Whitman's gift of copies of Leaves of Grass and Specimen Days, the other a request for the poet's autograph; fifth page—a request from E. L. Merrill for an autograph, and a fragment of another letter; sixth page—a portion of a letter to Whitman from C. W. Brink, M. D., and a piece of Whitman manuscript, headed, "Another Another I cross home to Jersey in the transparent shadows," thirteen lines, in pencil, a portion of a note published in Specimen Days under the date, February 6, 1877. With: a scrap of paper bearing the title, "Chronological forecast of Walt Whitman's life, and the successive publications of Leaves of Grass, etc."; and a printed version of the biographical outline from Bucke's book.
- Portraits, 1854-1940 and undated
  Contains painted portraits, sketches, engravings, etchings, and photographs of Whitman and of his brother, George, and sister, Hannah.
  - Portraits of Walt Whitman, 1854-1940 and undated
    Where artist and date of a portrait are known, they are included below. Reproductions of most of the portraits are included in Whitman Portraits, edited by Henry S. Saunders, call number PS3235 .S3 1946. Entries for those portraits appearing in Whitman Portraits include Saunders' catalog number. Saunders' book catalogues portraits according to Whitman's age, thus lower-numbered items generally refer to images of a younger Whitman. Listed alphabetically by artist or photographer. See also photographs in the Miscellany Series.
    - Anonymous
      - Photograph, circa 1854 (Saunders 5) (Box 11, Folder 14)
        Collotype print.
      - Photograph, 1869; Whitman with Peter Doyle (Saunders 29) (Box 11, Folder 15)
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 29.
      - Photograph, 1869; Whitman with Peter Doyle (Saunders 30) (Box 11, Folder 16)
        Description from Frey: Reproduced in the brochure describing the Trent Collection, issued by the Friends of the Library, Duke University, April, 1943.
      - Photograph, 1869 (Saunders 96)
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 96. Mounted and framed with Whitman's copy of the Victor Hugo letter, page 61, number 11.
      - Photograph, Brooklyn, 1871 (Saunders 35) (Box 11, Folder 17)
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 35. Laid in John Burroughs' Notes on Walt Whitman, 1871.
      - Photograph, 1872 (Saunders 38) (Box 11, Folder 18)
        Mounted.
      - Photograph, 1873 (Saunders 42) (Box 12, Folder 1)
        Carte-de-visite.
      - Photograph with Kitty and Harold Johnston, 1879 (Saunders 68) (Box 12, Folder 2)
        5.5 x 3.75 inches.
      - Photograph, 1888 (Saunders 100) (Box 12, Folder 3)
        Engraving after photograph.
      - Oil painting, 1889 (Saunders 105) (Box 12, Folder 4)
        Printed reproduction.
      - Portrait reproduced in The Review of Reviews, Vol. III, no. 14: 1891, Feb., p. 163
      - Photograph, undated (Saunders 37.1) (Box 12, Folder 5)
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 37.1. Mounted in edition of Leaves of Grass, Philadelphia, David McKay, 1884.
      - Photograph, Gribaydoff, undated (Saunders 37.1a) (Box 12, Folder 6)
        Engraving.
      - Photograph, tinted, undated (Saunders 70) (Box 12, Folder 7)
        Photograph fragile, damaged by water.
      - Photograph, undated (Saunders 101)
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 101. Mounted in volume containing the manuscripts on Whitman's last sickness. See page 67, number 25.
      - Photograph of bust by Sidney Morse, undated (Saunders 301) (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - Whitman portrait (Blatas), undated (Box 12, Folder 9)
        Photograph of Blatas portrait.
      - Photograph, 1890 (Saunders 112) (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Blatas, Arbit
      - Oil painting
        25.5" X 32.5"/35.5" X 41.5"
    - Brady, Mathew
      - Photograph, Washington, 1869 (Saunders 24) (Box 15)
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 24. Mounted and framed with a reproduction of another photograph and a postcard to Edward Carpenter, page 51, number 4.
      - Photograph (Saunders 45), undated (Box 12, Folder 11)
        2.25 x 3 inches.
    - Coughlin, Jack
      - Etching, undated (Box 20)
        Signed artist's proof.
    - Cox, George C.
      - Photograph (Saunders 92), 1887, Sept. (Volume 191)
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 92. Mounted and framed with two manu scripts, page 5, number 7.
      - Photograph (Saunders 92), 1887, Sept.
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 92; in sepia and smaller than the preceding example of the same photograph. Mounted and framed with a manuscript, page 18, number 1.
      - Photograph (Saunders 95), 1887, Sept.
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 95. Mounted and framed with manuscript, page 65, number 19, 7.
    - Edy Brothers, London, Ont.
      - 1880 Sept. 22 (Saunders 75)
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 75. Mounted and framed with a picture of Abraham Lincoln and a manuscript on Lincoln. See page 64, number 19, 4.
    - Gardner
      - Photograph, Washington 1863 (Saunders 21) (Box 12, Folder 12)
        3.5 x 5 inches.
    - Gilchrist, Herbert
      - Photo-intaglio from a drawing, undated; (Saunders 81.1)
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 81.1. Two copies, mounted and framed with manuscripts; see page 8, number 16, and page 27, number 36.
    - Gutekunst, F.
      - Photograph (reproduction), 1880; (Saunders 80) (Box 12, Folder 13)
        Description from Frey: A reproduction of a Gutekunst photograph, Saunders, Number 80.
    - Jaeckel, Willi
      - Lithograph, undated (Saunders 37)
    - Johnson, T.
      - Etching, 1891 (Saunders 95a) (Box 15)
        Description from Frey: 9 x 7% inches. Saunders, Number 95a. In a narrow black frame.
    - Johnston, Dr. John
      - Photograph, Whitman with Warren Fritzinger, 1890, July (Saunders 108) (Volume 194)
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 108. Mounted and framed with manuscript, page 9, number 19.
      - Photograph, With Warry, 1890 (Saunders 109) (Box 12, Folder 14)
      - Photograph, Whitman, solus, 1890 (Saunders 110) (Volume 203)
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 110. Mounted and framed with manuscript, page 27, number 35.
    - Kennedy, Bartlett F.
      - Photograph, Boston, The Pompous Photo, undated (Saunders 85) (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Kotz, E. Whittlesey
      - Charcoal sketch, 1887, 11 Feb. (Saunders 95e) (Box 15)
        Description from Frey: 18 1/2 x 13 1/2 inches; sketched from photograph, Saunders, Number 95. Mounted and framed with a Whitman autograph, "Walt Whitman Camden N J Feb: 11 '87."
    - Kruell, G.
      - Woodcut (Saunders 37.1b) (Box 20)
        Reproduction.
    - Kurtz, W.
      - Photograph, Whitman with Harry and Kitty Johnston, 1879 (Saunders 68) (Volume 195)
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 68. Mounted and framed with manuscript, page 9, number 20.
    - Linton, W. J.
      - Woodcut (reproduction), 1871 (Saunders 44a) (Box 12, Folder 16)
        copy with title page of 1876 "Author's Edition" of Leaves of Grass.
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 44a.
    - Pearsall, Frank
      - Photograph, undated (Saunders 31) (Box 12, Folder 17)
        Included with letter to William Sloane Kennedy, 1 Apr. 1890, a ticket to Whitman's lecture on Lincoln at Madison Square Theater 14 Apr. 1887, and a clipping from the Philadelphia Press16 Apr. 1887 describing the lecture. Cf. Correspondence From or By Whitman Subseries.
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 31. In board folder with Lincoln material, page 54, number 20.
      - Photograph, undated (Saunders 32) (Box 12, Folder 18)
        3.75 x 5.75 inches. By Frank Pearsall.
    - Pearsall, G. F. E.
      - Photograph, 1872 (Saunders 36) (Volume 19)
        Cf. Manuscript Poems Subseries: Poems not Appearing in Leaves of Grass.
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 36. Mounted in the volume containing the manuscript Table of Contents of Leaves of Grass. See page 10, number 25.
      - Photograph, 1872 (Saunders 36) (Box 12, Folder 19)
        Cf. Manuscript Poems Subseries: Notes for Poems.
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 36. Mounted in volume containing manu script notes on literature, page 36, number 28.
    - Phillips and Taylor
      - Photograph, 1883 (Saunders 48) (Volume 205)
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 48, reversed. Mounted and framed with manuscript, page 49, number 36.
    - Potter and Co., Philadelphia
      - Photograph, 1882 (Saunders 83) (Volume 140)
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 83. Mounted in volume containing the manuscript outline of Whitman's career. See page 63, number 19,1.
    - Sarony
      - Photograph, 1879 (Saunders 57) (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Schnelle, William G.
      - Three-colored cut, undated (Saunders 87.1) (Box 12, Folder 21)
        Description from Frey: In green, brown, and black; 5.5 x 7.25 inches. Two copies.
    - Schoff
      - Steel engraving, circa 1863 (Saunders 11a) (Box 12, Folder 22)
        4.5 x 6.5 inches.
    - attrib. Smith, William Russell
      - Oil portrait, undated
        Description from Frey: 17 1/2 x 13 1/2 inches; probably painted from a photograph. Attributed to William Russell Smith. In a white wooden frame.
    - Waters, G. W.
      - Sketch (reprod.), 1877 (Saunders 52)
        Description from Frey: Saunders, Number 52. Mounted in volume containing Bucke manuscript, page 63, number 17.
    - Woolf, S. J.
      - Lithograph, circa 1940 (Box 15)
  - Portraits of Others, 1862 and undated
    This undated subseries consists of renderings of Whitman's brother, George, and sister, Hannah. Listed alphabetically by name of subject of image.
    - Whitman, George W.
      - Anon.; hand-colored tintype, 1862 [?] (Box 11, Folder 13)
        Description from Frey: Tintype, hand-colored. With a wrapper, inscribed by R. M. Bucke: "Geo. W. Whitman W. W.s brother—Served in North ern Army 1861 to J6$—This photo probably taken about 1862— He was born 28 Nov 1829— Still lives (though very sick and paralysed 18 March 1899 RMB." Laid in the volume of George Whitman's letters, page 62, number 15.
    - Whitman, Hannah